מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ח, lamed chet, and
we pick up, we are a good deal behind, we pick up
at
the very bottom, like last word of ל"ז עמוד א'. lamed zayin
amud aleph. So we're going to try to keep up a good
pace today, even though it's a very juicy topic. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Okay, now on
ל"ט עמוד א'. lamed tet amud aleph. We taught over there. We're
going to the משניות Mishnayot in שביעית Shevi'it that relate to שמיטת
כספים, shmitat kesafim, and not just produce but שמיטת כספים shmitat kesafim
in general. המחזיר חוב לחברו בשביעית צריך שיאמר לו משמט אני. Hamachzir
chov lechaveiro bashevi'it tzarich sheyomar lo meshameit ani. For now we're getting
into some of the mechanics of how שמיטת כספים shmitat kesafim works.
Somebody comes during the שמיטה shmita year, now the language here is
during the שמיטה shmita year. רש"י Rashi says it means after שמיטה
shmita has passed and the debt has been annulled, but I want
to get back to that. Anyway, so somebody comes to pay back
a debt and you're supposed to say משמט אני. meshameit ani. You're
supposed to say to him like the creditor is supposed to say
to the debtor, "I annul the debt. I release you from it."
ואם אמר לו אף על פי כן, V'im amar lo af al
pi chen, but if the debtor says, "Nevertheless, I still want to
pay it back. Look, I feel bad, you lent me a thousand
dollars, it's nice that you're releasing me and that there's שמיטה, shmita,
but I want to make good on my
debt." יקבל הימנו. yikabel mimenu. You're allowed to take the money back
from him, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, וזה דבר השמיטה. V'zeh dvar hashmitah. This is
the matter of the שמיטה. shmita. So what does that so the
דבר dvar is word of דיבור, dibur, right, to speak, and therefore
what it's telling you is that you are supposed to release him
through words. You're supposed to basically say משמט אני, meshameit ani, I
release you. So that's interesting, right? Let's say you don't say that,
right? Is the idea of שמיטה shmita as משמטת כספים, meshameitet kesafim,
right? It says שמוט כל בעל משה ידו, shamot kol ba'al masheh
yado, etc., right? Is that telling you that you have an obligation
to annul the debt? We always assumed that it meant that שמיטה
shmita automatically annuls the debt. Let's say you didn't say this, is
the debt still annulled or not? So yeah, so the ראש Rosh
so it's a good question. You could say it's annulled but you
nevertheless have an obligation to personally reinforce that through your words. It's
not exactly clear the relationship between your verbal משמט אני meshameit ani
and the automatic sense that the debt is annulled. The ראש Rosh
has the best resolution, I think, check it but if I'm remembering
from memory, the ראש Rosh basically says the difference is during the
שמיטה shmita and after the שמיטה. shmita. The ראש Rosh basically says
that this is specifically בשמיטה, bishmita, that during the year of the
שמיטה, shmita, the debt still exists, but you are supposed to not
demand it. You are supposed to be שמוט. shamot. You are supposed
to say משמט אני. meshameit ani. Okay, so you're an active participant
in, because if you think about it, right, otherwise it's not like
there's a releasing from debts on שמיטה. shmita. שמיטה Shmita is when
everything else is released, but no, that guy still owes you money,
right? And it only gets annulled at the end of שמיטה. shmita.
So really, like, during שמיטה shmita you can collect your debts? Like,
that seems to deeply go against the sense we have about what
שמיטה shmita is about. The ראש Rosh actually says both are true.
During שמיטה, shmita, the debt exists and you're commanded not to demand
it, not to exact it, and it's וזה דבר השמיטה. V'zeh dvar
hashmitah. If somebody tries to pay it up during שמיטה, shmita, you're
supposed to say "I release you from it." After שמיטה, shmita, it
automatically is annulled. So the ראש Rosh actually has is it the
ראש Rosh or the ריצב"א Ritzba for the seventh year?
Well, no, because because well, maybe, but okay, but the point is
that you have to you have to prevent the automatic annulment, right,
if you want to collect it afterwards, right? During it, you can
go through the sabbatical through the שמיטה shmita year without actively collecting
it. Anyway, so that's a very nice way that the ראש Rosh
reads this idea of בשמיטה. bishmita. And that also explains why the
guy, if he says אף על פי כן af al pi chen
I want to return it, that you're supposed to accept it from
him because then he still owes you the money. The debt still
exists, right? It's just that you're not allowed to demand it. You
have to have an obligation to release him. If he wants to
pay it up on his own free will, right, so then fine,
that makes sense. There still is a debt there, it hasn't been
erased yet. Okay, so it's a very nice read of this idea.
If you read it the other way, then you could say that
even if the debt has been annulled or whatever, if a guy
wants to make good on money he borrowed, even if technically as
a sort of legal matter there's no debt, you know, then it's
the right thing to do to pay up. You got money from
a guy, you give it back to the guy. Sort of the
same way if you got a gift from somebody, if you got
an invitation from somebody for שבת Shabbos meal, you should reciprocate. You
know, it doesn't have to mean that there's an official legal debt,
but it still would be like the right thing to do. The
moral debt. It's a moral debt, right. Anyway, so but the ראש
Rosh reads it in this other way, which is a very, I
think, powerful way of reading it. Okay, so you're supposed to say
משמט אני, meshameit ani, and he's allowed and if he says אף
על פי כן, af al pi chen, you're allowed to accept it
from him. Now we're going to go to pushing that point about
אף על פי כן af al pi chen as a way of
getting your money back, and we're going to push it a little
bit. Let's take a look.
אמר רבה Amar Rabba says רבה, Rabba, or רבא, Rava, however you
say it, תלייהו עד דאמר הכי. talvei lei ad d'amar hachi. You
can basically string him up until he says this. Yeah, until he
basically says, even though you, you know, אף על פי כן af
al pi chen I want to return it to you. So you
twist his arm, not literally, but whatever. We'll see cases about it.
Anyway, you try to twist his arm to give it back. willingly
give it back even though he doesn't owe you the money. So
the גמרא Gemara says, איתיביה אביי. Eitivei Abaye. You're allowed to. So
it gets, it starts to get a little funny, right? איתיביה אביי.
Eitivei Abaye. So Abaye challenges. כשהוא נותן לו, Keshehu noten lo, אל
יאמר לו בחובי אני נותן לך. Al yomar lo be-chovi ani noten
lach. When he gives back, if he's choosing to give back the
money after you said משמט אני, mashmit ani, don't say I'm giving
this back to you because of the debt. The debt no longer
exists. You've released him from the debt. Okay, אלא יאמר לו, Ella
yomar lo, שלי הן ובמתנה אני נותן לך. Sheli hen u-v'matana ani
noten lach. I don't owe you the money, but I want to
give this to you as a gift. Okay, so if we're acknowledging
that it should not be given back in the context of paying
a debt, once if he is choosing to give it back, how
can you twist his arm to give it back if we're supposed
to not acknowledge that there's a real debt here? So the גמרא
Gemara says, so אמר ליה, Amar leh, so Rava said back, תליוהו
ויהיב. Talyuhu v'yahiv. Fine, you pressure him until he says I'm giving
it to you as a gift.
So you don't acknowledge that it's in the context of a debt,
but you try to persuade him, you know, it's really the right
thing to do. You know, I mean, he gave you all that
money. Okay, technically speaking, the debt doesn't exist anymore, but come on,
really, you know. Anyway, so that's what you do. You try to
get him to understand his moral responsibility and then he gives, but
he can't be giving it as payment of a debt. The debt
has already been erased, or if it's during שמיטה Shmitah the way
the הרא״ש Rosh understands, even if objectively it exists, the person is
being משמט, mashmit, is not demanding it as a debt. So you
pay it up, but you don't pay it up as paying of
a debt. Okay, it runs against the whole concept of what this
is all about. I know. So this is interesting, right? This is
the גמרא Gemara trying to, you know, Eddie, Eddie, Eddie, you're distract...
this is the Gemara trying to strike a similar balance to the
whole phenomenon of, you know, of the פרוזבול, pruzbul, right? But I
would say that I'm not so sure I would push it that.
I mean certainly when Rava says תליוהו ויהיב, talyuhu v'yahiv, he's trying
to sort of like, you know, yes, it is a little like
undermining. It is sort of acknowledging like there's some injustice here, right?
It's nice to release people, but if a person's able to pay
back and has the means or whatever, you know, it's appropriate to
pay it back. Also, again, remember, according to the הרא״ש, Rosh, the
way the Rosh understands it, the debt really does exist. What the
Torah is telling you is during the שמיטה Shmitah year, you're not
supposed to demand, you're not supposed to like exact payment, but the
debt still does exist. So it works a little bit better according
to the way the Rosh understands. Okay. So anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: now we're going to have some cases. אבא
בר מרתא דהוא אבא בר מניומי. Abba bar Marta de-hu Abba bar
Minyumi. Abba bar Marta is also known as אבא בר מניומי. Abba
bar Minyumi. הוה מסיק ביה רבה זוזי. Hava masik beih Rabbah zuzei.
He owed Rabbah money. אייתינהו ניהליה בשביעית. Ayitinhu nihaleih b'shvi'it. He brought
it to him on שביעית. Shvi'it. Again, for the הרא״ש Rosh it's
beautiful, I mean during the שמיטה Shmitah year, right? So אמר ליה,
Amar leh, משמט אני. Mashmit ani. So Rabbah did the right thing
and he said to him משמט אני. mashmit ani. So שקלי ואזל.
Shaklei v'azil. So fine, he took his money and he left. Good.
Okay. אתא אביי. Ata Abaye. Now again, this is the same Rabbah
and Abaye that were before, right? Remember Rabbah said you can pressure
him and Abaye challenged that, or it might have been Rava, but
anyway, Abaye's Rabbah's תלמיד. talmid. Rabbah didn't get his money back. Even
though Abaye said you're not supposed to pressure him, or challenged that
idea, let's see what Abaye does right now.
אזל אביי Azal Abaye went. אשכחיה דהוה עציב. Ashkecheih d'hava atziv. He
saw that he was, he saw that Rabbah was in anguish. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, אמאי עציב מר? Amai atziv Mar? Why are you,
why are you so upset? אמר ליה, Amar leh, הכי הוה מעשה.
Hachi hava ma'aseh. Here's what happened. He owed me 10,000 dollars, he
came to pay back, I did what I was supposed to do,
I said משמט אני, mashmit ani, and then he just left. He
didn't understand the like, little game we're supposed to play, not the
nuance, but like, we didn't, he didn't keep to the script. Okay.
אזל לגביה. Azal l'gabeih. So Abaye went to him. אמר ליה, Amar
leh, אמטיתנהו זוזי למר? Amteitanhu zuzei l'Mar? Did you bring your money
back to, you know, to pay back the Master? אמר ליה, Amar
leh, אין. In. Yes. אמר ליה, Amar leh, ומאי אמר לך? U-mai
amar lach? And what did Rabbah say to you? אמר ליה, Amar
leh, משמט אני. Mashmit ani. He told me that he was releasing
me.
אמר ליה, Amar leh, ואמרת ליה אף על פי כן? V'amarta leh
af al pi chen? Did you say to him nevertheless, I still
want to pay it back? אמר ליה, Amar leh, לא. Lo. He
said to him, well, I know, I didn't say that. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, אי אמרת ליה אף על פי כן הוה שקיל מינך?
Ei amarta leh af al pi chen hava shakil minach? Had you
said to him אף על פי כן, af al pi chen, he
would have been happy to take it from you. השתא אמטינהו ניהליה
ואימא ליה אף על פי כן. Hashta amteinhu nihaleih v'eima leh af
al pi chen. So you know what? It would be a good
idea now to bring the money back to him and to say
אף על פי כן. af al pi chen. אזל אמטינהו ניהליה ואמר
ליה אף
על פי כן. Azal amteinhu nihaleih v'amar leh af al pi chen.
אזל אמטינהו ניהליה ואמר ליה אף על פי כן שקלינהו מיניה. Azal
amteinhu nihaleih v'amar leh af al pi chen shaklinhu mineih. So Rabbah
was happy to take the money. אמר. Amar. Then Rabbah said about
him, לא הוי בידיה דהאי צורבא מרבנן מעיקרא. Lo havi b'yadeih d'hai
tzurva me-rabanan me-ikara. That, that Torah scholar, you know, did not know
what he was doing initially, like, you know, he wasn't paying attention,
he forgot his lines. Okay, he should have, he should have learned
enough Torah. It was a משנה, mishna, that you're supposed, now the
משנה mishna doesn't say you're supposed to say
אף על פי כן. af al pi chen. It says if the
guy says it you can accept it, but he should have understood
that that's his moral responsibility. That was actually a משנה. mishna. משנה
שביעית. Mishna Shvi'it. That was a משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna says
if he says אף על פי כן af al pi chen you
can take it from him. Okay, so the funny thing though is
that אביי Abaye that resisted the idea of pressuring the guy basically
went ahead and applied subtle pressure to the guy. Okay, so I
mean it was his רבי Rebbe that wasn't getting his loan paid
back. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, said... excuse
me, אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, נאמן אדם לומר פרוזבול היה
בידי ואבד. ne'eman adam lomar pruzbol hayah beyadi ve'avad. Meaning, a person
can claim he had a פרוזבול pruzbol and he lost it. Okay,
and he doesn't have to actually show a פרוזבול. pruzbol. So here's
another קולא kula about פרוזבול. pruzbol. Before we saw that certain תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim maybe didn't even have to write it, you know,
maybe could just verbally make a declaration, or there was a position
in שמואל Shmuel that automatically there would be assumed a פרוזבול. pruzbol.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying not that far, but he's saying
that even if you don't have to produce it to prove that
you've written it.
Okay, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? כיון דתקינו רבנן פרוזבול, keivan detikinu
rabanan pruzbol, since it's a... they've established it and it's a way
of addressing וזה, vizeh, לא שביק התירא ואכיל איסורא. lo shevik heteira
ve'achil issura. People would not have abandoned a permissible way of exacting
וזה vizeh and done it in transgression. So we assume that everybody
took care of it. Now, obviously sometimes people are negligent and they
forget, but nevertheless this is another nice big gaping loophole, but he
doesn't say you're allowed to lie and say this, but you know,
anyway, once you don't have to produce it in court, it obviously
basically is yet another way to make it very easy for people
to... you know, collect their debt. כגון זה פתח פיך kegon zeh
ptach picha and excuse me, לא שביק התירא. lo shevik heteira. כי
אתו לקמיה דרבא, ki atu lekamei deRava,
now when it came to רבא, Rava, a case like this, and
the guy didn't... wouldn't produce a פרוזבול, pruzbol, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so רבא Rava said to him, מידי פרוזבול הוה לך ואבד? midi
pruzbol havah lach ve'avad? Is it possible you had a פרוזבול pruzbol
and you lost it? So כגון זה פתח פיך לאלם הוא. kegon
zeh ptach picha le'ilem hu. This is a case of open up
your mouth to the mute. Meaning, you know, which is funny, cause
you imagine if a guy actually did write a פרוזבול pruzbol and
he lost it, he would have said something. He'd be like, "Oh
my god, I had it, I can't find it," or whatever. But
the guy said nothing. Right, it's after שמיטה, Shmita, I'm sorry. And
the guy said, "I don't know what to say." רבא Rava says,
"Well, maybe you had a פרוזבול." pruzbol. He says, "Oh yeah, I
did have a פרוזבול pruzbol and I lost it." So anyway, it
does sound like there's a little wink and nod going on here.
Okay. I said you're not supposed to do that, but... No, you're
supposed to, you're supposed to. Okay. Okay, yes. תנן, Tenan, we taught.
וכן בעל חוב שמוציא שטרו ואין עמו פרוזבול הרי אלו לא יפרעו.
vechen ba'al chov shemotzi shtaro ve'ein imo pruzbol harei elu lo yifare'u.
Wait,
wait a minute. We got a משנה Mishnah that says that if
the creditor takes out his... the document and it doesn't have a
פרוזבול, pruzbol, he cannot collect. So it seems you need to produce
the פרוזבול. pruzbol. תנאי היא, Tannai hi, it's a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. דתניא, Detanya, המוציא שטרו וצריך שיהא עמו פרוזבול חכמים אומרים אינו
צריך. hamotzi shtaro vetzarich sheyehei imo pruzbol chachamim omrim eino tzarich. You
don't have to actually produce the פרוזבול. pruzbol. Another obvious possible explanation
is that at the earlier time of the משנה, Mishnah, as we've
been seeing, פרוזבול pruzbol was a more weighty and serious thing even
when it was created, and then later it became a much more
trivial and easier thing to use to satisfy the requirements of קרקע
karka and the other types of requirements. So it was obviously even
a more liberalizing of that... of that option. Yeah, לא שביק התירא
ואכיל איסורא, lo shevik heteira ve'achil issura, is that like also a
generalized principle? Yeah, sometimes we do. We just assume that if somebody
had just as easy of an option to do it in the
התר heter way, that we presume that they did it. Okay, but
anyway, let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. So now
that was the... that was the סוגיא sugya of פרוזבול, pruzbol, very
fun סוגיא. sugya. Now we move on to a completely different סוגיא,
sugya, which is interestingly, although we're obviously in the broad rubric here
of תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, this משנה Mishnah does not mention תיקון
עולם, tikkun olam, and it's not even going to be clear from
the משנה Mishnah what case is the תקנה takkana and what the
תיקון עולם tikkun olam is that is being achieved, and that'll be
left to the גמרא Gemara to unpack. So let's take a look.
Yes. Quick question. Did you say that after שמיטה Shmita it's automatically
annulled? Yes. At the... on the last day of שמיטה, Shmita, like
the last minute of שמיטה. Shmita. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of the
eighth year, it's... the debt no longer... is annulled.
And רב Rav said you're not supposed to demand it on... during
שמיטה. Shmita. Right. When is this little interaction taking place? During שמיטה.
Shmita. Yeah, according to the way the ראש Rosh read it. Right.
Okay. עבד שנשבה ופדהו. Eved shenishba ufadahu. So a slave is taken
captive and he was redeemed, right? They... they ransomed him back to
the master. So אם לשם עבד, im leshem eved, if he was
redeemed for the sake of going back into... into servitude, slavery, ישתעבד.
yishtabed. So then he goes back to his master, or whatever, he
goes back into servitude. אם לשם בן חורין, Im leshem ben chorin,
however, if he was redeemed, presumably not by his master, other people
found out that a slave was being taken captive and taken away,
you know, by this foreign force, and they redeemed him and they
figured as long as they're redeeming him, they might as well set
him free. It wasn't their slave. So presumably that would be the
circumstances. לא ישתעבד, Lo yishtabed, then he does not go... he does
not get re-enslaved, he actually does go free. All that makes a
lot of intuitive sense. רבן גמליאל אומר בין כך ובין כך ישתעבד.
Rabban Gamliel omer bein kach uvein kach yishtabed. Either way, he remains
a slave. Okay, again, not clear exactly who's doing the תיקון עולם
tikkun olam and what the תיקון עולם tikkun olam is that is
being achieved, assuming that there is a תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, which
would be the only explanation for what it's doing in this פרק.
perek. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. במאי עסקינן? Bemai
askinan? What's the case? אילימא לפני יאוש, Ilima lifnei ye'ush, if the
master has not given up hope of retrieving the slave... Now you
have to realize that even though we're obviously talking about a human
being, the slave is legally considered to be property, right? So therefore
a similar principle... imagine that they hadn't taken my slave but they
had taken my, you know, my car, right? So the same property...
the general principles about יאוש ye'ush from שינוי רשות, shinui reshus, once
I give up hope of retrieving it, it can be possessed by
the person who took it, right? Or by the... a third... a
third party that takes a hold of it. People know those general
ideas, right, about אבידה aveida and גניבה. geneiva. You give up hope
and somebody else gets it, it becomes their object. So that's thank
you. That's so much. That is the basic ideas that is operating
here, okay? So אילימא לפני יאוש, ileima lifnei ye'ush, if it's before
the master's given up hope, right, so לשום בן חורין אמאי לא
אישתעבד? leshum ben chorin amai lo ishtabed?
Just because he's redeemed for the purpose of being a free man,
again, it's not the master who's redeeming him for that purpose, so
why does he go free? He's still totally my property. What right
do you have? It's very nice that you bought my car off
of this גנב, ganav, but it's still my car. Give me my
car back. You know, maybe I have to pay you some money,
right, because you paid money to get it, but why do I
lose ownership over it? All right, it's still mine. Okay, so אמאי
לא אישתעבד? amai lo ishtabed? אלא לאחר יאוש, ela le-achar ye'ush, it
must be that I've given up hope. And since I've given up
hope, that basically means I'm no longer master over it. We won't
go to the exact details of יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush u-shinui reshus,
okay, and therefore you are free to redeem that slave and to
set him free and for the purpose of him being free. So
if that's true, לשום עבד אמאי אישתעבד? leshum eved amai ishtabed? So
but okay, but if I've given up hope and he stops being
mine and he stops being a slave, then why when you redeem
him to remain in servitude does he remain in servitude? He should
already be a free man. I've given up hope and maybe that's
enough to set... okay, so we'll see. But that's the question. So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so now we're going to have two answers
to this. אמר אביי לעולם לפני יאוש, amar Abaye le-olam lifnei ye'ush,
it's before יאוש. ye'ush. לשום עבד אישתעבד לרבו ראשון, leshum eved ishtabed
le-rabo rishon, obviously,
because he's still mine and I haven't given up hope. So לשום
בן חורין, leshum ben chorin, now here's the question, so I haven't
given up hope, totally my property, somebody redeems him as a free
man, why does he go free? לא אישתעבד לא לרבו ראשון ולא
לרבו שני, lo ishtabed lo le-rabo rishon ve-lo le-rabo sheni, not for
now, then he, I can't enslave him and the people that redeemed
him can't enslave him. לרבו שני לא, le-rabo sheni lo, obviously the
people that freed him can't enslave him, they redeemed him, they redeemed
him to go
free. דהא לשום בן חורין פרקיה, de-ha leshum ben chorin parkei, they
redeemed him to be a free man. Now, why don't I get
him back? It's my slave, I didn't give up hope. Very nice
you redeemed him, I don't care what you had in mind, it's
my slave, give him back to me. So no, לרבו ראשון נמי
לא, le-rabo rishon nami lo, דילמא מימנעי ולא פרקי, dilma mimnei ve-lo
parkei,
because we want to incentivize people to redeem the slave. Okay, it
is true the slave is still property, but remember, he's owned by
Jews, presumably well taken care of, he has obligations in מצוות, mitzvos,
he's taken by these marauding troops, right, he's going to be, he
might be mistreated, right, you know, they're violent marauding troops, whatever they
are, he's not going to have the opportunity to do מצוות. mitzvos.
We are not happy with this situation, objectively, that it's a bad
thing, right, that the slave is now taken by these other but
you know by this foreign power, whoever these people might be. So
we want the slave to be not in that situation. Okay, so
whether it means going back to the master, whether it means going
free, we want him to not be in that situation. So we're
going to incentivize people to redeem him. And we're going to tell
all of those bleeding heart liberals out there that if you redeem
this slave, you have an opportunity to set him free. Normally he
wouldn't be able to be set free because he was being held
by his master. But now if you redeem him for the sake
of him going free, he will go free. And that will incentivize
people to go ahead and to redeem him. Okay, I'm being a
little facetious, but you know, maybe it's also just like
the way so רש"י Rashi works explains it is, if he's just
a slave, I'll say eh, big deal, it's just a slave. But
if I know that if I redeem him he goes free, then
I'm thinking about him as a potential free man, that'll make me
more feel like oh, this is somebody important that's worth to redeem.
Okay, so that might be the less nice way of saying it.
But the words are ולא פרקי, ve-lo parkei, and not to free
him. No, if you do not, if he does not go free,
right, if you say that he has to go back to the
first master, people will hold back and not redeem him. And that's
why he doesn't go back to the first master. Even though it's
before יאוש, ye'ush, he logically he should go back to the first
master. Right. But if he does, people will hold back and not
redeem him. So the language is מימנעי ולא פרקי, mimnei ve-lo parkei,
to prevent... no, not prevent. People will hold back on their own
and won't redeem him if you tell him to go back to
the first master. So to prevent people from not redeeming him, to
incentivize, we're going to say that if you redeem him he'll go
free. I don't think people are that noble. I think just the
opposite. In other words, you know, if I don't get anything out
of it, why do I redeem him? But if I can get
him as a slave, it's less than market value. No, but people
are, right, but there's a sense of a מצוה, mitzvah, there's a
מצוה mitzvah to be, you know, פודה שבויים. podeh shvuyim. So I
might think, yeah, there's a מצוה mitzvah of פדיון שבויים, pidyon shvuyim,
but eh, let's all be, you know, it's like it's really if
they're only free Jews. Like, you know, we sort of feel כנעני's
Kenaani in a second class status. Oh, you're telling me he'll be
a free Jew, then I sort of see this as my obligation
of פדיון שבויים. pidyon shvuyim. That's sort of how it gets worked
out. Okay, so that's the idea. So according to that, the תיקון
עולם tikkun olam is that he goes free when he's redeemed to
go free, even though there's no יאוש. ye'ush. He's totally his master's
property. So according to that, the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is that
he goes free when he's redeemed to go free, even though there's
no ייאוש. yeush. He's totally his master's property, but we're going to
incentivize people to redeem him and for the sake of him going
free. That'll help or if they do it for that reason, he'll
go free, and that'll be the תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. That's the
position of the חכמים. Chachamim. Comes רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר בין
כך ובין כך ישתעבד. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer bein kach u’vein
kach yishtabed. No,
I'm sorry, I don't buy any of that stuff. You're still totally
owned by the master. כסבר כשם שמצוה לפדות בני חורין כך מצוה
לפדות עבדים. Kasavar keshem shemitzvah lifdot bnei chorin kach mitzvah lifdot avadim.
There's just as much of a מצוה mitzvah to be פודה שבויים
podeh shvuyim if they're free men if they're slaves. And therefore, it's
I don't think you have to incentivize people. Okay, so that's the
question of, that's one way of framing the תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam.
The תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is that he goes free if that's
why they were freeing, if that's why they were redeeming him, even
though he shouldn't. It was before ייאוש, yeush, but that'll help get
people to redeem him. That's one approach. Okay, that's who was that?
That was who said that approach?
אביי. Abaye.
Okay, רבא אמר. Rava amar. Now Rava has obviously is going to
take the other tack. No. Rava says לעולם לאחר ייאוש. Leolam le'acher
yeush. We're dealing
לאחר ייאוש. le'acher yeush. If it's before ייאוש, yeush, you're right, totally
my property, I wasn't מיאש. meya'esh. I don't care what you had
in mind, give him back to me. Maybe I have to pay
you for your expenses, we'll figure that out, but give him back
to me. That's before ייאוש. yeush. לאחר ייאוש, Le'acher yeush, that's when
we're talking. ולשום עבד ישתעבד. U’leshum eved yishtabed. Now, if you redeemed
him for a slave לאחר ייאוש, le'acher yeush, you know why he's
still a slave even though it's לאחר ייאוש? le'acher yeush? You get
to enslave him. If you redeemed him because you wanted to take
him as your slave, it's like a ייאוש ושינוי רשות. yeush v'shinuy
reshut. Even though I was מיאש meya'esh and I lost my claim
to him, he was not yet a free man. You redeemed him
from the from the captors, so you take possession of him. That's
if it's לשום עבד. leshum eved. Now, לשום בן חורין, Leshum ben
chorin, if it's to be free, לא ישתעבד לא לרבו ראשון ולא
לרבו שני. lo yishtabed lo lerabo rishon velo lerabo sheni. Then obviously
he's free and he can't be enslaved by either. לרבו שני לא
דלשום בן חורין פרקיה. Lerabo sheni lo d'leshum ben chorin parkei. For
the second master, because you're not trying to enslave him. ולרבו ראשון
למה לא דהא לאחר ייאוש הוא. U'lerabo rishon lama lo deha le'acher
yeush hu. That's after ייאוש. yeush. That's a very nice explanation that
has the חכמים Chachamim saying the עיקר הדין. ikar hadin. The חכמים
Chachamim aren't saying the תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam, they're saying the עיקר
הדין. ikar hadin. It's לאחר ייאוש, le'acher yeush, so he can be
taken by a second person, but if the second person doesn't take
him, doesn't want to possess him, then he's released by the person
holding him, nobody's taking a claim to him, so he goes free.
He's not owned by anyone and he goes free. Okay, so that's
the חכמים Chachamim are saying it's לאחר ייאוש le'acher yeush and what
they're saying is מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin that okay, that he's either
taken by taken possession by the second person or he's freed based
on the second person's intentions. Okay. That's רבא. Rava. So what's רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? And Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
is making the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam and it's a different type
of a תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר בין
כך ובין כך ישתעבד. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer bein kach u’vein
kach yishtabed. Either way he's enslaved. כדחזקיה. Ked'Chizkiyah. Now why? You know
it was מיאש, meya'esh, nobody's trying to take possession of him.
Well, okay, that would be a separate question, how do you determine
that? But that's not our issue right now. דאמר חזקיה, De'amar Chizkiyah,
because חזקיה Chizkiyah said, מפני מה אמרו בין כך ובין כך ישתעבד?
mipnei mah amru bein kach u’vein kach yishtabed? Why did they say
either why did רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel say
either way he's enslaved? שלא יהא כל אחד ואחד הולך ומפיל עצמו
לגייסות ומפקיע עצמו מיד רבו. Shelo yehei kol echad v'echad holech umapil
atzmo legaysot u'mafki'ah atzmo miyad rabo. Because if a slave knows that
if I go ahead and get taken by captives, it's a way
to get out of, you know, to get away run away from
my master, I'll get redeemed and I'll go free and I'll go
free. Well, maybe, but anyway they said like, you know, they had
to deal with the concern of runaway slaves, so therefore they made
a special תקנה takkana that the slaves go back to their masters
even if logically they should be free because there was ייאוש yeush
and and the second one did not want. Now which master does
he go back to? It's not a total clear. רש״י Rashi says,
I mean Rashi says, where's Rashi?
A minute, בין כך ובין כך ישתעבד. bein kach u’vein kach yishtabed.
Rashi says לרבו ראשון. lerabo rishon. He clarifies, which makes sense because
if you want the idea is if you want to disincentivize slaves
to runaway, you want to let them know whatever they try they're
going back to their master. Not whatever, because if the second one
wanted to take possession of him, presumably the second one would take
possession of him. But even if the second but either they'll maybe
they'll be taken possession by the second one, but if the second
one is doing it for the sake of, oh no, excuse me,
Rashi says בין כך ובין כך ישתעבד לרבו ראשון. bein kach u’vein
kach yishtabed lerabo rishon. Excuse me, Rashi might be understanding that even
if the second one redeems him for the purpose of enslaving him
to himself, we are making a תקנה takkana that he's always going
back to the רבו ראשון, rabo rishon, right? So I mean look,
it's very difficult to read these, like you know, these are like
you think about these runaway slave laws in the south and all
of this, this is what's happening. Okay, but it also makes you
appreciate the issue about תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam
is not always these nice sort of liberal ideas, you know, that
we think about that sometimes people assume is תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam.
The תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is we got a world in which
slaves are an important commodity and important part of the economy and
we can't have them running away. So the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam
is that even in situations where they should be able to be
going free, or at least going to a different master who might
be a better master, right, and there maybe we want to incentivize
them to runaway if they're being so oppressed. No, no, no, our
תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is they're always going to get returned to
their first master. We can't have slaves running away, right? So it's
a very different way of looking at it. Okay, so one way
is the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is that they go free. when
they're redeemed to go free and it's before יאוש, Ye'ush, and that's
to incentivize people to redeem them. And the other תיקון עולם, Tikkun
Olam, it's for לאחר יאוש, L'achar Ye'ush, and they really should either
go free or go to the second master, but the תיקון עולם
Tikkun Olam is they always go back to their first master. All
right, everybody got that? Those sort of two scenarios? Yeah. What does
the Torah mention about a runaway slave who is not to be
returned? Isn't that only Hebrew slaves? That's also understood in the context
of running from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
And it's yeah, so it's a good question, but it's and I
think we're actually going to get to it later in the גמרא,
Gemara, but it's not directly applicable, but it's a very good question.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. Okay, so מיתיבי. Meitivei. אמר להם רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar
lahem Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
So here we have a ברייתא. Baraita. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel said to the חכמים: Chachamim: כשם שמצווה לפדות את
בני חורין, כך מצווה לפדות את העבדים. Keshem shemitzva lifdot et bnei
chorin, kach mitzva lifdot et ha'avadim. It's the same way it's a
מצווה mitzvah to redeem
free people, it's a מצווה mitzvah to redeem slaves. So why is
he saying that? That works perfectly according to אביי Abaye because אביי
Abaye says that that's why the חכמים Chachamim said he goes free,
to incentivize people, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
said no, you don't need to incentivize them, it's the same מצווה.
mitzvah. So בשלמא לאביי, Bishlama l'Abaye, דאמר לפני יאוש, d'amar lifnei Ye'ush,
it's before יאוש, Ye'ush, so היינו דקאמר כשם. haino d'ka'amar keshem.
So that's why the תנא קמא Tana Kama is saying we've got
to let him go free because that'll incentivize people, and רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel saying you don't have to let
him go free, they don't need to be incentivized. Okay, אלא לרבא,
דאמר לאחר יאוש, Ela le-Rava de-amar le-achar yeush, but רבא Rava says
it's לאחר יאוש, l'achar Ye'ush, and the חכמים Chachamim are just saying
the normal הלכה, halacha, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is coming and creating this תקנה takkanah to make all the
slaves go back, so היי כשם, hai keshem, what do you mean
he's saying, oh look, there's the same מצווה mitzvah to redeem them?
That's like irrelevant to the discussion. משום דחזקיה הוא, mishum d'Chizkiyah hava,
he should be saying what about חזקיה, Chizkiyah, what about making sure
that slaves don't run away?
So אמר לך רבא, amar lach Rava, רבא Rava would say back
to you, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל לא הוה ידע מאי קאמרי רבנן.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel lo hava yada mai kamri rabanan. Okay, this
is a nice way out of it. He didn't know what the
rabbis were saying. Rabbis said, you know, in this case slave, this
case go free. He says I don't know what you're talking about.
He says הכי קאמר להו: hachi ka'amar lehu: אי לפני יאוש קאמריתו,
e lifnei Ye'ush kamritu, if you're saying before יאוש Ye'ush and then
you're coming up with this weird idea that they go free to
incentivize people, you're wrong, so היינו כשם, haino keshem, you're wrong, you
don't need to incentivize people before יאוש. Ye'ush. And אי לאחר יאוש,
e l'achar Ye'ush, and if it's לאחר יאוש l'achar Ye'ush and what
you're saying is that it makes sense that he goes free if
that's how he was redeemed,
then כדיחזקיה, kedichizkiyah, I also say you're wrong because of חזקיה, Chizkiyah,
that we should actually make a תקנה takkanah to make sure that
all slaves go back to their masters. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ולרבא דאמר, u'l'Rava d'amar, according to רבא Rava who
says לאחר יאוש l'achar Ye'ush ולרבו שני, u'l'rabo sheni, it's לאחר יאוש
l'achar Ye'ush and according to the חכמים Chachamim who don't have a
תקנה, takkanah, if he's redeemed to be to be enslaved by the
second master, he is enslaved by the second master. It's like a
יאוש ושינוי רשות. Ye'ush v'shinui reshus. So the גמרא Gemara says: שני
ממאן קני ליה? sheni miman kanei lei? Who did the second master
buy him from? Okay, meaning now the captors. But the question is,
is that the point, the גמרא Gemara sort of assuming if the
captors have no rights to the slave, I mean there's a whole
discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim how to exactly conceptualize this. But the
idea is like this: if the captors have no right to the
slave, the master אמיאש amyash from the slave, he basically at that
moment is ownerless. Why doesn't he go free at that moment? Okay,
if I steal your object, you're מיאש, miyash, the גנב ganav is
קונה, koneh, isn't he? Ah, so in general we say that by
normal cases of a normal גנב, ganav, there's something called קניין גניבה
kinyan gneivah or קניין גזילה, kinyan gzeilah, that he has some type
of ownership over that, not full ownership, but some type of an
ownership over that. Now that's the גמרא's Gemara's question that it's asking
here. Where do we have this idea that these non-Jewish captors can
get ownership, a partial ownership over the slave? And the presumption is
that if they didn't have that, then if there was יאוש Ye'ush
and the owner was מיאש, miyash, the captors have no rights on
the slave, so that itself would make him a free man. So
the idea that he still remains a slave and he can be
transferred to the hands of another master presumes that the captors have
some control and some ownership over him. So the גמרא Gemara says
where do we know that from? Okay, so let's take a look.
How was he a slave in the first place? For example, just
one example? One example, he was bought, he was enslaved, he was
taken captive like like people became slaves. Non-Jews were at war, they
you know the the victorious
troops enslaved the the other the other thing and then sold them
and a Jew bought them. Yep, that would be an example. And
we're actually going to and we're actually going to see some of
that right now. Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, so שבאי גופיה מי קני ליה? shavai gufei mi kanei lei?
How did the how did the captor get any ownership over the
slave? So the גמרא Gemara says: ממאן קני ליה משבאי? miman kanei
lei mishavai? From the captor. שבאי גופיה מי קני ליה? shavai gufei
mi kanei lei? אין, קני ליה למעשה ידיו. in, kanei lei l'ma'aseh
yadav. He doesn't own him fully as property, but he at least
has rights to his labor. Okay, now by the way, I do
want to say that this is similar to an idea, it partly
has to do with the nature of owning human beings as property
and obviously and you know to what degree can they be owned
as property or just owned for their labor? Slaves that are non-Jews
are owned as property. But the other issue is about how you
understand קנייני גניבה וקנייני גזילה. Kinyanei Geneiva v'Kinyanei Gezeila. If I go
out and I steal Michael's car, right? We just said that there's
something called קניין גניבה. Kinyan Geneiva. Now what does it mean? I
own it? I don't own it; I mean I would have to
give it back to him if he finds me. But what it
means is, here's actually one application of that הלכה. Halacha. Well, it
could mean I'm responsible, but ownership normally also suggests rights, not just
responsibilities. And one application of this is that if I actually, Michael
finds me and I give it back, I don't have to pay
him any rental fees. Okay, which is a funny idea. Here I
was, I stole it from him, but nevertheless, the fact that it
was in my possession and I was in control when I was
trying to take possession of it gave me some de facto rights
of usage. It's a bizarre idea, but that's the idea of קנייני
גניבה. Kinyanei Geneiva. Okay, and קנייני גזילה, Kinyanei Gezeila, right?
Yeah, I mean, yes, and I pay it back and I don't,
again, pay any usage fees. So here, that's exactly being paralleled here.
The captors own him, not fully as property, but they own him
that they're entitled to his labor. But because they have that type
of a partial ownership over him, a de facto and partial ownership,
he does not go free even after יאוש Yeush and he transfers
into the hands of the third party who frees him to enslave
him. That's what we call קנייני גוף? Kinyanei Guf? All right, yes.
Anyway, but let's not go there. So the גמרא Gemara says, like,
wait, let's look at... apply to a husband and wife, for the
work of her hand? That's exactly what Michael said. Yeah, there are
parallels to that. Or no, it wasn't exactly what Michael said. Anyway,
yes, there are parallels, the whole idea of מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeha.
Let's read another line. Jon, you had a question? Or, okay, let's
read another line. It says like this, okay, למעשה ידיהם, L'ma'aseh Yadeihem,
דאמר ריש לקיש, D'amar Reish Lakish, מנין לעובד כוכבים שקנה עובד כוכבים
למעשה ידיו. Minayin l'oved kochavim shekanah oved kochavim l'ma'aseh yadav.
Now here, I explained it because it was a perfect parallel to
a גניבה גזילה Geneiva Gezeila situation. But now what ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish is doing, or the גמרא Gemara is doing by quoting ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, is it's putting it in the larger context of
general idea of enslaving human beings. Okay, and here is a strange
idea, which is that Jews can own non-Jews as slaves as property,
but non-Jews can only own non-Jews as slaves as like... as like
an indentured servant. They own them for their מעשה ידיו, Ma'aseh Yadav,
but not fully as property. Very strange and deeply disturbing idea. Okay,
מנין לעובד כוכבים שקנה עובד כוכבים למעשה ידיו? Minayin l'oved kochavim shekanah
oved kochavim l'ma'aseh yadav? How do you know a non-Jew can own
a non-Jew, if he's trying to enslave him, for his, you know,
for his labor, but not fully as property, but he does own
him for his labor? שנאמר, Shene'emar, the verse says, וגם מבני התושבים
הגרים עמכם מהם תקנו עבד ואמה. V'gam mibnei hatoshavim hagarim imachem mehem
tiknu eved v'amah. So there you go, Dov, that's your פסוק. Pasuk.
From those that are... that dwell among you, you can buy from
them slaves. That's the פסוק, Pasuk, buy slaves from the non-Jews dwelling
among you. Okay, so the גמרא... Gemara... so the דרשה Derasha is
the following: מהם תקנו, Mehem tiknu, אתם קונים מהם, Atem konim mehem,
you buy from them slaves and they become fully slaves, they become
property. Okay, you're property. ולא הם קונים מכם, V'lo hem konim mikem,
but they cannot buy slaves from you. You can't sell yourself as
a slave to non-Jews. Now, you can, as we're going to see,
because Michael correctly remembers, in those פסוקים Psukim it talks about a
Jew selling himself as a slave to the non-Jews, but the point
is, not as property, for מעשה ידיו, Ma'aseh Yadav, okay? So you
can... so I'm going to sort of anticipate already the end of
the גמרא Gemara just to clarify this. You can buy them as
property, they cannot buy you as property. They can buy you as
slaves for your מעשה ידיו, Ma'aseh Yadav, but not... right. ולא הם
קונים זה מזה, V'lo hem konim zeh mizeh, and they can't
buy each other as property. So here's the irony. They go ahead
and they, you know, attack another nation, enslave the people, they only
own them for their מעשה ידיו. Ma'aseh Yadav. Then they go ahead
and they sell them to the Jews, and now the Jews own
them as property. Okay, so they can't own you as property, they
can't own each other as property. The only people that can be
owned as property, this is so deeply disturbing I can't even say
it, the only way a slave can be owned as property is
a Jew owning a non-Jew. Okay, a Jew... what? Unless they assume
the following social reality. Yeah. That it's a תיקון Tikkun by Jewish
law not to allow a pagan to own a human being as
property because it'll be too abusive. Uh-huh. So it has to be
somewhere better... Okay, that's interesting. Okay, that makes it better. Better for
a pagan to be owned as property by a Jew than for
a pagan to be free... but it's not like they weren't forced...
I don't know about free, that's another conversation. But the idea, certainly,
to think about like לא שיעבוד מצרים, Lo Shibud Mitzrayim, that like...
but it's still... yeah. We can't trust the non-Jews and the pagans,
right, to own each other as property. The only people that can
be trusted to own slaves as property is the people who themselves
were enslaved and owned as property. Right. Okay, anyway, that's the point.
The only people that can be owned as property is you can
own them as property. Okay, then the ברייתא Baraisa goes on. Okay,
יכול, Yachol, let's go back talking about פרוסבול. Pruzbul. יכול לא
יהיו קונים זה את זה. Yachol lo yihiyu konim zeh et zeh.
Now the ברייתא Baraisa continues, maybe they can't own one another? So
the גמרא Gemara interrupts the ברייתא Baraisa before it finishes its sentence,
like some of you do here with me. So what do you
mean? אמרת לא הם קונים זה מזה. Amarta lo hem konim zeh
mizeh. What do you mean maybe they can't own one another? You
said they can't own one another. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is
what the ברייתא Baraisa is saying. ולא הם קונים זה מזה לגופו.
V'lo hem konim zeh mizeh l'gufo. They can't want own to their
body. יכול yachol לא יקנו זה את זה. lo yiknu zeh et
zeh. Now the ברייתא Braisa continues, maybe they can't own one another.
So the גמרא Gemara interrupts the ברייתא Braisa because before it finishes
its sentence, like some of you do here with me. So what
do you mean? אמרת Amarta לא הן קונים זה מזה. lo hein
konim zeh mi-zeh. What do you mean maybe they can't own one
another? You said they can't own one another. Now הכי קאמר, hachi
ka'amar, this is what the ברייתא Braisa is saying: ולא הן קונים
זה מזה לגופו, ve-lo hein konim zeh mi-zeh l'gufo, they can't own
one another as fully as property. You know, יכול לא יקנו זה
את זה למעשה ידיהם, yachol lo yiknu zeh et zeh l'ma'ase yedeihem,
but maybe they shouldn't be even able to own one another even
for their מעשה ידיהם. ma'ase yedeihem. אמרת Amarta קל וחומר. Kal va-chomer.
Now that's a קל וחומר. Kal va-chomer. עובד כוכבים ישראל קונה, Oveid
kochavim Yisrael koneh, a non-Jew can own a Jew for his labor,
right? That's the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה Torah that you sell
yourself to a non-Jew, you're taking, you know, if you have those
cases where you where you have to all those in the context
of שמיטה Shmita where you have to raise money and whatever, you
sell yourself as a slave. So they can own Jews as, you
know,
for their מעשה ידיהם. ma'ase yedeihem. קל וחומר Kal va-chomer עובד כוכבים
עובד כוכבים לא כל שכן, Oveid kochavim Oveid kochavim lo kol she-ken,
certainly they can own one another for מעשה ידיהם. ma'ase yedeihem. So
they own one another for מעשה ידיהם, ma'ase yedeihem, they own you
for מעשה ידיהם, ma'ase yedeihem, you actually can own them לגופו. l'gufo.
Okay, and that explains the שבי shavi captures the slave, he owns
the slave למעשה ידיהם, l'ma'ase yedeihem, and then he's bought by another
Jew, and the other Jew now is able to take possession of
him לגופו, l'gufo, right? You got the idea? Right? The actual full
ownership of property, right? The slave doesn't go free because the non-Jew
is still in sort of controlling and has a degree of ownership
which prevents the slave from being freed even though I've given up
hope of getting him back. And then the
other Jew is now able to take possession of him לגופו l'gufo
because a Jew can own him לגופו. l'gufo. Okay, so that's how
that works when he redeems him in order to enslave him.
Right, so רש"י Rashi discusses, alright, so if you want to look
at the רש"י Rashi let's look at that. I mean, I was
starting to focus on it purely economically, but it is important, you're
right. So let's look at רש"י. Rashi. So what's the implication about
לגופו? l'gufo? שצריך הימנו גט, she-tzarich heimenu get, right? One issue is
how does a person stop being a slave? If you own them
as property, you need actually a writ of manumission, you need a
גט get that changes their status. If you only own them למעשה
ידיהם, l'ma'ase yedeihem, then you can more just like
renounce your ownership, right? It's sort of like I could be, I
don't know, מפקיר mafkir my property, I you know, I release, I
no longer make any claim to it. So whereas if it's really
about full ownership of identity and as person as property, you need
to change their status and you need a גט. get. That's one
issue. או אם יברח הימנו ויתגייר מותר בבת ישראל, o im yivrach
heimenu ve-yisgayyer muttar be-bat Yisrael, שאין גופו קנוי לחברו. she-ein gufo kanui
l'chavero.
Or
that's also related to the issue about personal status, right, that as
long as he's being owned by a non-Jew, he can become Jewish.
Right? So you know, the idea that his full personal status and
identity is defined, you know, by him being a slave, that's only
when he's owned לגופו. l'gufo. So there's two aspects of being owned
לגופו. l'gufo. One is a purely דיני ממונות dinei mamonot aspect. You
know, like again, a simple example
is I put something on your slave, you own it because it's
on your property. It's just a simple fact. He's a piece of
property, right? That's one relevant aspect of being owned לגופו l'gufo as
opposed to if you own his labor, you don't actually own his
body, the הלכה halacha wouldn't apply. But רש"י Rashi correctly, and thank
you for pointing it out, points to the idea that owning a
person as property goes more than just a technical question of how
much do you own. It, if he's owned as property, it's a
status issue. His whole status and identity is a slave. And if
his status and identity is a slave, not just that you have
rights to his labor, then that means that, right, to change that
status you need a גט שחרור, get shichrur, you need a writ
of manumission. It's also like the way you need a גט get
for a woman, it's about changing status. The person can't make a
choice, "I'm going to become Jewish, I'm going to whatever," right? It's
his whole status is defined, you know, by that sense of ownership.
So that's a very important to point out about that's part of
what owning לגופו l'gufo means. או אם יברח הימנו ויתגייר אז יהיה
אסור בבת ישראל, o im yivrach heimenu ve-yisgayyer az yihye assur be-bat
Yisrael, right? Because if if he's מגייר migayyer he's מותר בבת ישראל.
muttar be-bat Yisrael. If he's what? If he's owned by a non-Jew,
okay, and then he's מגייר, migayyer, so a non-Jew owns another non-Jew
למעשה ידיהם. l'ma'ase yedeihem. That non-Jew who's a slave can be מגייר
migayyer because the other, his identity isn't defined by him being a
slave. And now he's Jewish, and now he's just Jewish and somebody
else owns his מעשה ידיהם. ma'ase yedeihem. He's like an עבד עברי
Eved Ivri or whatever. He can still go ahead and marry בת
ישראל, bat Yisrael, he's fully Jewish. But he's owned לגופו, l'gufo, his
whole identity is defined by it, he doesn't get to redefine his
status, he doesn't get to be מגייר. migayyer. If he runs away,
he doesn't like run away. He doesn't get to choose to be
מגייר, migayyer, okay? His whole status is defined by him being a
slave. If I as the master want to free him, that's a
different story. Okay. I don't understand how to read this קל וחומר.
Kal va-chomer. How do you make a קל וחומר? Kal va-chomer? If
a non-Jew can own a Jew for מעשה ידיהם... ma'ase yedeihem... We
have no words, עובד כוכבים ישראל. Oveid kochavim Yisrael. What do you
mean? קל וחומר Kal va-chomer עובד כוכבים Oveid kochavim ישראל Yisrael קונה,
koneh, if an עובד כוכבים Oveid kochavim owns a Jew for מעשה
ידיהם, ma'ase yedeihem, עובד כוכבים עובד כוכבים לא כל שכן, Oveid kochavim
Oveid kochavim lo kol she-ken, certainly they can own a non-Jew for
מעשה ידיהם. ma'ase yedeihem. No, can I just put the קונה koneh
for you? All right, ואימא הני מילי בכספא. v'eima hani mili be-kaspa.
Now, one minute. All maybe this only is through money. A non-Jew
owns a Jew, how does a non-Jew take possession of a Jew
for מעשה ידיהם? ma'ase yedeihem? When the Jew sells himself to the
non-Jew. Okay, but or as רש"י... Rashi... He says in general, how
would a non-Jew take possession of land? Think of slaves as land.
Through money and we learned that out from פסוקים. Pesukim. Okay, so
the whole idea that they can take possession of מעשה ידיהם, Ma'aseh
Yadayim, we have the paradigms of a Jew selling himself as a
slave to a non-Jew or non-Jew taking possession of land. The paradigms
are through purchase. Okay, but בחזקה מניין? B'Chazaka Minayin? But in this
case, it's not through there's no purchase. He stole him. He took
him captive. And that's taking direct physical possession of him. Okay, so
it's a type of an idea of חזקה. Chazaka. Normally חזקה Chazaka
is I'm willingly selling you my land and you do some act
to demonstrate mastery over it and you take possession of it. You
go and you build a fence or you dig a hole. This
is a forceful חזקה. Chazaka. Okay, this תוספות Tosafot calls this כיבוש
מלחמה. Kibbush Milchamah. Okay, this is basically like might makes right, okay,
that I go ahead and I and I just seize property in
war. I seize your slave and I take it captive. That that
idea of that fact that he's fully under my control and I
seized him gives me some rights to him. Where do we get
that idea? Okay, because that's what happened. These non-Jewish captors stole my
slave, and now we're saying they own him למעשה ידיהם. L'Ma'aseh Yadayim.
Where do we know that idea exists? Okay, בחזקה מניין? B'Chazaka Minayin?
How do you know that works with חזקה? Chazaka? הוי בחזקה ובחזקה
לא, Havi b'Chazaka u'v'Chazaka lo, maybe it doesn't work בחזקה? B'Chazaka? אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa says, עמון
ומואב טיהרו בסיחון. Amon u'Moav tiharoo b'Sichon. No, we know it from
another case of
חזקה, Chazaka, of כיבוש, Kibbush, כיבוש מלחמה, Kibbush Milchamah, where it's the
case about עמון ומואב, Amon u'Moav, right? סיחון Sichon took over the
lands of עמון ומואב. Amon u'Moav. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael took over
the lands of סיחון, Sichon, right? Everybody remember those stories in, you
know, whatever, in,
no, but in שופטים, Shoftim, right, and also starting in במדבר Bamidbar
or whatever. Anyway, but we weren't allowed to seize lands of עמון
ומואב, Amon u'Moav, right? The תורה Torah says ואל תצר את מואב
V'Al Tetzar et Moav etc. We were allowed because they stopped being
lands of עמון ומואב. Amon u'Moav. They became lands of סיחון Sichon
because he captured them in war. Okay, there that nation captured them
in war. So you see there's an idea of כיבוש מלחמה Kibbush
Milchamah when something is captured by force and captured in war, that
makes it belong to that next nation. Okay, so don't read any,
now people going to talk about the most political and contentious topic
ever that we've ever had here, besides this contemporary situation. Anyway, so,
anyway, so that belongs to that nation. So similarly, if that could
be true about the land, presumably it's true about the people that
were captive, captured, and therefore there is this idea of כיבוש מלחמה,
Kibbush Milchamah, something taken by force actually gives them rights to that
thing.
Okay, so, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: עכו"ם מעכו"ם
Akum m'Akum כוכבים, kochavim,
that's when they took land from non-Jews took land from non-Jews that
they have the idea of taking possession by force. עכו"ם מישראל מניין?
Akum mi'Yisrael minayin? How about if they take forceful possession of something
that's owned by Jews? How do you know that that gives them
rights to it? So the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב, Dichtiv, the verse
says וישב ממנו שבי, Vayishbi mimenu shevi,
and they took a captive. And the fact that it's called a
שבי, Shevi, it doesn't say that they took a person captive, but
they took a captive captive, means that that person became a captive.
Okay, and that changed that person's identity. All right, so now we've
established that when a, they can't like capture a free man and
enslave him, a Jew. Yes, they can, but למעשה ידיהם, L'Ma'aseh Yadayim,
not לגופו. L'Gufo. Okay, so non-Jews can, again, own one another למעשה
ידיהם, L'Ma'aseh Yadayim, own Jews למעשה ידיהם. L'Ma'aseh Yadayim. The only person
that's owned לגופו L'Gufo is a Jew owning a non-Jew. Again, very
disturbing how we explain it. Anyway, but in this case the non-Jew
took my slave captive, אני מייאש, ani meya'esh, they still own him
למעשה ידיהם, L'Ma'aseh Yadayim, even though it was a forceful seizing, they
own him למעשה ידיהם. L'Ma'aseh Yadayim. And therefore, he doesn't go free
even though אני מייאש, ani meya'esh, and he's able to be transferred
to the possession of another Jew who wants to buy him and
enslave him. All right, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר
רבי שמעון בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Shimon bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan, עבד שברח מבית האסורים יצא לחירות. Eved shebarach mibait
ha'asurin yatza l'cherut.
How about if he actually ran out of, he escaped from his
captors? Okay, so an עבד Eved escaped, it says it says here
from like a prison, but it's understood in this context he escaped
from his captors, he goes free. ולא עוד אלא שכופין רבו וכותב
לו גט שחרור. V'lo od ela shekofin rabo vekotev lo get shichrur.
And not only does he go free, we would force his last
master to write a writ of manumission to make sure that his,
you know, freedom was clear and unquestionable. שלחו לבי דכורש. Shaltechu l'bei
d'Koresh. Well, maybe anyway. Okay, but let's just read the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara is totally ignoring that פסוק, Pasuk, we'll get to
that פסוק Pasuk later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תנן. Tnan.
Now let's see if this fits. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, בין כך ובין כך ישתעבד. Bein kach u'vein
kach yishtabed. Either way he's enslaved. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל מקום
ששנה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו, Kol makom sheshanah Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel bemishnateinu, whenever רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel appears
in our משנה, Mishnah, הלכה כמותו, Halakha k'vato, we rule like him,
חוץ מערב וצידון וראיה אחרונה, Chutz me'Arev v'Tzidon v'Raya achrona, except these
three cases which I'm not even going to bother to explain. Now,
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, says
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which means he's enslaved. But there's another teaching
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which is that if he escapes his
captors, he goes free. So which is it? Is it, right, is
he enslaved according to this? He should always be enslaved once he's
taken captive. This is an עבד Eved escaping from a Jewish master?
No, an עבד Eved that was taken captive like in our משנה,
Mishnah, but then escaped. escaped his captors. So then why does he
need a גט שחרור Get shichrur if it's only מצאה ידו? Matzeih
yadav? Because well okay that's a good question might depend before after
יאוש. Yeush. Okay but let's anyway see what let's first figure out
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So it says like this. So the גמרא
Gemara wants to know: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says... רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we rule like רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he's always enslaved. And here רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is saying that when he escapes his captors, he goes
free. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: קשיא. Kashya. Alright. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Everybody's got their theory. בשלמא
לאביי, Bishlama le-Abaye, says the גמרא, Gemara, it's good according to אביי,
Abaye, I'm glad that you're so involved. בשלמא לאביי, Bishlama le-Abaye, מוקי
לה להאי לפני
יאוש. moki lah le-hai lifnei yeush. So what's אביי, Abaye, he makes
sense of this. When does רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel say he's enslaved and when do we rule like that? לפני
יאוש. Lifnei yeush. Like before יאוש, yeush, so he totally remains enslaved,
end of story and that's the case in the משנה. Mishnah. והא
דאמר, Ve-ha de-amar, when it says that he escapes his captors he
goes free, that's after יאוש. yeush. Now he asks: so why does
the master have to write a גט שחרור? Get shichrur? Okay so
that's a separate question which is, let's say forget that I was
מיאש, meya'esh, let's say I said explicitly, "I am מפקיר mafkir my
עבד, eved, I renounce any ownership over my slave," does he need
a גט שחרור Get shichrur or not? So we're going to see
in a few minutes hopefully, or if not whatever soon, that he
still might need according to many opinions a גט שחרור Get shichrur
because that gets to the difference between owning him as property and
personal status. And it might be that if I'm מיאש meya'esh or
I מפקיר mafkir him, I no longer own him as property, I
can't demand his labor, nothing. But his identity is still that of
a slave. His personal status is still that of a slave. And
to change the status issue, I still might need a שטר שחרור.
Shtar shichrur. Okay? And as you said that an עובד כוכבים Oved
kochavim cannot own... true, he doesn't own him, I'm מיאש meya'esh from
him, he's not... he cannot be enslaved, I cannot demand any work
from him. But he's still not fully חייב במצוות, chayav be-mitzvot, he
can't marry a Jewish woman, because it's a personal status issue that's
not necessarily changed by a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot fact. A personal
status issue might need a שטר, Shtar, a שטר Shtar to change
his identity. Does Jewish law require an עובד כוכבים Oved kochavim to
write a גט שחרור? Get shichrur? No, it requires his original master.
He's my slave. He was taken captive. He escaped his captors. He
goes... so once he escaped his captors, he goes free and I
now am compelled to write him a שטר שחרור. Shtar shichrur. רבא
רישא, Rava reisha, okay, okay, that was what was in the... anyway,
but we will see about that issue about ownership and identity and
status, again going back to that רש"י Rashi we read before. Okay,
so according to אביי Abaye it makes sense. We rule like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he remains a slave before
יאוש, yeush, but when he escapes after יאוש, yeush, so it's after
יאוש, yeush, nobody owns him, he goes free, and okay I write
a שטר שחרור Shtar shichrur to address the status issues, that's very
nice. אלא לרבא ela l'Rava, דאמר לאחר יאוש, d'amar l'achar Ye'ush, but
according to רבא Rava that even after יאוש yeush we make this
תקנה takanah that everybody goes back to their master, because we don't
want slaves running away. So we're always going to send slaves back
to their master. And according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we rule
that way. So what's this slave doing going free?
אלא לרבא דאמר לאחר יאוש קשיא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן, Ela le-Rava
de-amar le-achar yeush, kashya de-Rabbi Yochanan a-de-Rabbi Yochanan, it's a contradiction. So
אמר לך רבא, Amar lach Rava, רבא Rava will say to you,
טעמא מאי משום דחזקיה? Ta'ama mai mishum de-Chizkiyah? Wait a minute. Why
do we make slaves go back after יאוש yeush if nobody's enslaving
them? Because of חזקיה, Chizkiyah, because we don't want slaves to you
know, to escape, I mean to run away from their masters. ברח
שאני, Barach shani, we would not apply that when he actually has
escaped from his captors as opposed to having been redeemed. Why? What
difference does it make? ברח שאני. Barach shani. השתא לקטלא מסר נפשיה
אפקורי אפקיר נפשיה לגיסות? Hashta le-katla masar nafsheih, apkorei afkeir nafsheih le-gayisot?
If he's willing to risk his life to run away, he obviously...
because presumably the penalty would be death if you ran away from
your captors. So if he's willing to risk his life to run
away, he certainly not intentionally putting himself in that situation. Right? Do
you remember the reason for חזקיה Chizkiyah why we send slaves back
to their masters? So they don't intentionally let themselves be taken captive.
Everybody with me? You remember that? Right? So in order so that
they don't say "Oh, I'll let myself be taken captive, it'll only
improve my lot" or whatever, then no, no, no, if you're taken
captive you're going back to your master. Okay. But this guy's demonstrated
how he's willing to risk his life to not be a captive
because if he's found escaping, he'd be put to death. So in
that case, maybe we have רחמנות rachmanus on him or we certainly
don't need this תקנה takanah in such a case when somebody's really
willing to risk their life. Okay, clearly they did not intentionally put
themselves in that situation. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
אמתיה דמר שמואל, Amateih de-Mar Shmuel, the maidservant of שמואל, Shmuel,
אשתבאי, ishtava'i, was taken captive. פרקוה, Parkuh, whoever, some people redeemed her,
לשום אמהותא, le-shum amahuta, to remain a servant for שמואל. Shmuel. They
figured they'd do him a favor. So they redeemed... okay. ושדרוה ליה,
Ve-shadruh leih, and they sent her back to him. שלחו ליה, Shalchu
leih, and they sent him a message. אנן כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל
סבירא לן. Anan ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel sevira lan. We hold like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that once redeemed a
slave always goes back to the master. את, At, you שמואל, Shmuel,
you might want to be a big צדיק tzaddik and not take
her back. אי נמי כרבנן סבירא לך, I nami ke-rabbanan sevira lach,
even if you hold like the Rabbis that say when she's redeemed
to be free she goes free. אנן משום אמהותא פרקינה לך. Anan
mishum amahuta parkinah lach. Don't worry about it. We redeemed her to
remain your slave, so keep her, okay, our gift. Okay, so פרקינה
לה, parkinah lah, we did it for you. ואינהו סברו, ve-inhu savru,
אנן ושמושך פרקינה לה, anan u-shumshach parkinah lah, ואינהו שרו לפניה ve-inhu
sharo lifnei יאוש. ye-ye-ye'ush. Now here's the only problem: they assumed that
the case was before יאוש, ye'ush, but that wasn't actually the situation.
ולא היא לאחר יאוש הוה, ve-lo hi le-achar ye'ush hava, and Shmuel
actually had already been מייאש meya'esh from her.
Okay, and if he's been מייאש, meya'esh, maybe the whole debate of
Rabban Gamliel and the חכמים Chachamim was before יאוש, ye'ush, right? לאחר
יאוש, le-achar ye'ush, now okay,
it was might have been לאחר יאוש, le-achar ye'ush, but they was
still doing it like לשום עבד le-shum eved or something. All right,
so why still? So let's take a look. But not for themselves
as a slave, and Shmuel had no interest in taking her as
a slave.
ושמואל לא מיבעיא השתעבודי לא משתעבד בה אלא גיטא דחירותא נמי לא
צריכה. ve-Shmuel lo miba'ya ishtabudei lo mishtabed bah ela gita de-cheiruta nami
lo tzericha. But now only that, he said she's a total free
person even without a writ of manumission. And here gets to the
question of: once you lose your monetary ownership, does the slave automatically
become a free person or did they need a writ to change
the personal status? And Shmuel says that the two are intimately intertwined.
And if you don't own them in a monetary way, then they
don't need anything else, they're completely a free person. Okay, דאמר שמואל,
de-amar Shmuel, שמואל לטעמיה, Shmuel le-ta'ameih, דאמר שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, Shmuel says,
המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות ואינו צריך גט שחרור. ha-mafkir avdo yatza le-cheirut
ve-eino tzarich get shichrur. If you renounce ownership over your slave, he
goes free and he does not even need a writ to change
his personal manumission status, which means not only can you not enslave
him, but he's fully חייב במצוות, chayav be-mitzvot, can marry a Jewish
spouse or whatever, full halakhic status as a free person. His halakhic
status changes with his monetary status. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the verse says,
וכל עבד איש מקנת כסף, ve-chol eved ish miknat kasef, the slave
of a man. Sorry, עבד איש eved ish ולא עבד אשה? ve-lo
eved isha? I don't get it. So he can't be a slave
of a woman? What does it mean slave of a man? אלא
עבד שיש לו רשות רבו עליו קרוי עבד. ela eved she-yesh lo
reshut rabo alav karui eved. שאין לו רשות רבו עליו, she-ein lo
reshut rabo alav, once the master does not have any rights over
him, monetary rights, אין קרוי עבד, ein karui eved, his personal status
changes as well. So this was a case of לאחר יאוש. le-achar
ye'ush. Shmuel did not wasn't going to repossess her. They didn't want
to possess her. So she went free. It was like הפקר hefker
and therefore didn't even need a writ of manumission. Okay, let's just
read one more story quickly. אמר רבי אבא בר זוטרא, amar Rabbi
Abba bar Zutra, האמתא דרבי אבא
בר
זוטרא אשתבאי, ha-amta de-Rabbi Abba bar Zutra ishtavai, the maidservant of Rabbi
Abba, were taken captive.
פרקה parkah ההוא תרמודאה, hahu tarmuda'ah,
a
certain Tarmudean, a certain non-Jew, redeemed her. לשום אנתתא, le-shum inteta, as
in he wanted to take her as a wife. שלחו ליה, shalchu
lei, so some Jews sent to Rabbi Abba and they said and
they didn't want this non-Jew to take her as a wife. So
they said like this: שלחו ליה לדידיה, shalchu lei le-didei, אי יאושי
אייאשת שדר לה גיטא דחירותא. i ya'ushi aya'ishta shadar lah gita de-cheiruta.
So if you want, so they said, look, do the right thing
and send, give your slave a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. Now she's
in the hand of this non-Jew who wants to marry her, give
her שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So like what? What's that going to
do? So the Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case?
אי דמצי פרקי לה, i de-matzi parki lah, if these people are
trying to help out and redeem her, למה ליה גיטא דחירותא? lama
lei gita de-cheiruta? Why do they need him to send her שטר
שחרור? shtar shichrur? Redeem her and send her back to the master.
ואי דלא מצי פרקי לה, ve-i de-la matzi parki lah, if they
can't get enough money to redeem her, כי שדר לה גיטא דחירותא
מאי הוה? ki shadar lah gita de-cheiruta mai hava? What's it going
to help to send her שטר שחרור? shtar shichrur? She's being taken,
held by the non-Jew. I don't understand, what's this שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur going to do? She's being held by a non-Jew. So the
Gemara says: לעולם דמצי פרקי לה, le-olam de-matzi parki lah, they have
the money to redeem her, okay, or theoretically, but they need to
raise it. וכיון דמשדר לה גיטא דחירותא, ve-keivan de-mashdar lah gita de-cheiruta,
but again, it's similar to the issues before about people are more
incentivized to redeem somebody if they're free. So they said him: look,
free your slave in the hands of the non-Jew, then people will
know that if they redeem her, she'll go free, she'll be a
free person. Then they'll feel: oh, a free person is being held
captive, they'll be more incentivized to redeem her. Okay, חבורי מחברי אהדדי
ופרקי לה, chavuri mechavrei ahadadei u-parki lah, then people will gather together,
we'll be able to raise the money. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, and
if you want I can say, לעולם דלא מצי פרקי לה, le-olam
de-la matzi parki lah, they didn't have the wherewithal to redeem her,
but וכיון דמשדר לה גיטא דחירותא, ve-keivan de-mashdar lah gita de-cheiruta, once
if you send her this שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, מיבזא באפי, mivza
be-apei, then it'll be public that she was a slave. This non-Jew
doesn't want people to know that she was a slave. Okay, so
it'll be public that she's a slave, he'll no longer feel, he'll
feel embarrassed to be having her as his wife, and therefore he'll
lower the price and it'll be easier for us to redeem her.
Right now we can't afford it. But if you make it public
that she's a slave and you send the שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
he'll come down with the price and we'll be able to redeem
her. ומפרקי לה. u-mifarki lah. נו, nu, ואמר מר, ve-amar mar, but
didn't the master teach, חביבא להו האמנתא דישראל טפי מנפשייהו? chaviva lehu
hamanta de-Yisrael tfei mi-nafsheihu? Ah, but you know the non-Jews, they'll even
take our, you know, some such wonderful good buy, they'll even take
our animals, so why would he be embarrassed that she's a slave
of a Jew? That won't embarrass him to take her as a
wife. So the Gemara says: הני מילי בצינעא, hani milei be-tzina, that's
if nobody finds out about it. They're happy to do that. אבל
בפרהסיא, aval be-farhesia, to be publicly known as his wife, זילא בהו
מילתא, zila behu milta, that's embarrassing. So therefore, once it's known she's
a slave, he'll come... come down on the price and therefore we'll
be able, she was a slave and we'll be able to redeem
her. You see, even according to that, we're better off letting her
say she was a slave because we'll be able to redeem her
cheaper. The גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
They bring a proof. מעשה באדם אחד, maaseh beadam echad, a story
of one person, שהשיא את בנו, shehishi et beno, he married off
his son in לוד, Lod, ונכנסו אצלו, venichnesu etzlo, and people came
into his house to the חתונה. chatunah. Now, listen to this, this
is a גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, it's one of
the most incredible stories you've ever heard. It's on דף קי"ד. daf
kuf yud daled. A father is making a wedding for his son
in לוד. Lod. ונכנסו אצלו, venichnesu etzlo, and people came in to
the meal. והיה שם, vehayah sham, and there was there, are you
ready? רבי יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava. רבי יהודה בן
בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava was the one that was killed, you
know, at the time of the גזירה gezeira of the Romans for
giving סמיכה. semicha. This was a giant of a man. He's sitting
at the wedding. And you know, people come to weddings, they see
everything. ונכנסו אצלו, venichnesu etzlo, everybody came in and he saw that
the woman who was the mother of the חתן, chatan, the wife
of this host, was handing out glasses of wine to everybody. Now
she had her arms covered. ונראו זרועותיה, veniru zeroateiha, but for some
reason, maybe as she was pouring the wine, her sleeves went up
and her arms were exposed. They saw her arms. Now listen to
what they saw. You ready? וראו אותה, verau otah, and they saw
her, שהיא כבויה. shehi kivuyah. Do you know what that means? כבויה
kivuyah means it was burnt. There was a big brand on her
arm. Like you brand cattle. Now, why would she have a brand
on her arm? This was a sign that she was a slave.
When they would take slaves, they would brand them to show who
they belong to. They had a big brand on her arm. Now,
as soon as the guests saw that, what did they realize? Wait
a minute, she's a slave? A non-Jewish slave? She's not a Jewish
woman? Now, if she was a slave and she was never freed,
and she married a regular Jew, she can't marry a Jew. Her
children are slaves. The son who just got married is a slave.
The whole חתונה chatunah is nothing. The marriage is not a marriage.
So people started to whisper. And what did they say? She must
be a slave. Look at her arms. She has a brand on
her arms. אמר להם, amar lahem, so this host, the father of
the חתן, chatan, told everybody, I see you're whispering. What are you
whispering about? Because my wife has a brand on her arm? Let
me tell you why. My wife was once captured and taken into
captivity as a Jew, a Jewish woman. And she was taken into
captivity. And the non-Jews who captured her, wanted her to serve their
idols, to give herself over to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And she
refused. And because she refused, look what they did to her. She
was tortured. They took a red-hot iron and they burned her arms
to try and force her to serve their gods. And she still
didn't do it. You think she's a slave? That's not a slave's
mark. That's a mark of a צדקת. tzadeket. That's a mark of
a holy woman who gave her life rather than serve idols. And
the גמרא Gemara says, look at this. When the people heard that,
what did they do? Everybody immediately believed him. And they went and
they gave him more money and they were more happy with him
than before. They weren't only happy with the meal, but they gave
him more money. And the גמרא Gemara says, what do you see
from here? That you see even though we said she's not believed
to say she was a slave, here it says clearly she was
believed. If they're ready to believe it was a גזירה, gezeira, they'll
believe it. So why didn't we believe it in our משנה? Mishnah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, because there was a proof. There was
a brand. Since there was a brand, you have to explain the
brand. So either you say it's a slave or it's a גזירה.
gezeira. And because she's a fine woman and she's a Jewish woman,
we're ready to believe it was a גזירה. gezeira. But in the
משנה Mishnah where there's no brand, there's nothing, she just comes and
says it, there we don't believe her. Wait till you hear the
next story of the גמרא. Gemara. It's even more unbelievable.